we all want to avoid the cloaked bones
of death holding its sithe for as long
as possible and it turns out there's two
things that you can do that have a
massive impact in protecting you from
its bony fingers I know Health
influencers throw around hyperbolic
phrases like massive and incredible and
effects and all that stuff but I'm not
exaggerating as you'll soon see so let's
get into what they are what the signs
shows and what you can do to gain these
massive effects the first habit is
pingpong and the other is pretend
smoking
Twizzlers no no it's as you can see from
the study cardiorespiratory Fitness and
sauna use but the Intriguing thing is
how effective they are paired one is far
more powerful than the other but they
both seem to provide additive benefit in
the study the researchers Quantified the
amount of sauna use and
cardiorespiratory Fitness of over 2,000
participants in their mid-50s some had
cardiovascular disease and some didn't
but the researchers assessed these two
variables along with many others that
we'll get into shortly at Baseline and
then tracked over 26 years how many
people died of cardiovascular disease
and how many people died well in general
they were then able to stratify across
low sauna use High SAA use low
cardiorespiratory Fitness and would you
guess it high cardiorespiratory Fitness
and combinations of the conditions so
low sauna use was two times or less per
week and low cardiorespiratory Fitness
was under 30 milliters per kilogram per
minute so that's a V2 measure if you're
familiar if we pop open those data we
can see cardiovascular disease caused
mortality on the left and all cause
mortality on the right right and you can
see the corresponding colors related to
low and high levels of each condition
FSB isn't the Russian security service
but frequency of sauna baths and CRF is
cardiorespiratory Fitness we can see the
time p on the horizontal axis and the
amount of CBD mortality that's
cardiovascular disease mortality and
overall mortality on the vertical axis
so if the lines go up that's worse
clearly the bluish purple line and the
green line indicate worse results and
those happen to be the lowest in
cardiorespiratory Fitness with an
improvement with frequent sauna bathing
the green line however when
cardiorespiratory Fitness is high
mortality risk gets crushed into the
depths of Hell okay I'm actually being a
bit dramatic but clearly it gets crushed
into the depths of
Hell the issue with these data is
longtime physionic viewers will attest
is the fact that these are simple
associations so it doesn't account for
any other factors confounding factors
like body weight socioeconomic status
smoking high blood pressure and so on
you get the picture fortunately I did
mention the researchers collected a
bunch of data on these 2,000
participants and they did a number of
adjustments controlling for many factors
and they also reanalyzed the data taking
those factors into account and here are
the results I realized this isn't easy
to read but have no fear I'll walk you
through it because there's some changes
that seem to occur when accounting for
these variables so on the left side we
clearly see the high and low levels of
both key factors that we're interested
in and the two outcomes mortality now up
top we see different models these
correspond to the statistical analyses
that account for a variety of factors so
model one for example accounts for age
only model two accounts for age weight
smoking blood pressure cholesterol and
these other factors I'll list on screen
model 3 accounts for all the previous
factors but also socioeconomic status
and C reactive protein which is an
inflammatory marker so if we focus on
the most adjusted model model three we
see that the reference is low
cardiorespiratory Fitness and low sauna
bathing frequency if the risk goes below
one that indicates reduced risk
and we clearly see all the conditions
have reduced risk so if you pull any one
lever improved cardiorespiratory Fitness
or more sauna
bathing again mortality risk is reduced
across the board however there's
something important to be said about
this because one clue keeps popping up
across the data I've been analyzing a
good number of studies on sauna and
cardiorespiratory Fitness and in so
doing I've put together a variety of
ways of figuring out your
cardiorespiratory Fitness without having
to see an exercise physiologist and I've
also put together protocols based on the
most effective sauna protocols used in
the studies both of those guides along
with the extended version of this video
which includes even more fun science are
part of the physionic Insiders
membership and guess what that also
includes live sessions with this face
right here and a private monthly podcast
written research reviews and more it's a
steel I tell you if you want access to
all that just sign up using the
physionic Insiders Link in the
description I hope I'll talk to you
there that clue that I'm referencing is
the fact that the majority of the effect
seems to be driven by cardiorespiratory
Fitness even the researchers point out
that the greatest and most consistent
effect on reducing mortality is
cardiorespiratory Fitness not sauna that
said sauna is still beneficial
especially when cardiorespiratory
Fitness is low but it just doesn't
compare head-to-head at least on these
metrics now I should also mention a few
more things before we get to the
takeaways here one This research is
limited to a single measure meaning the
cardiorespiratory Fitness and sauna and
all that jazz was measured at one time
point and then never again so this means
that these results are predictive based
on a single measurement studies that
would make measurements over time say
every I don't know 5 years would offer
us much greater granularity on what
matters when it matters and so on we
just don't have that here two this study
is only in men and while I guess that
the results would be roughly the same
for women women also have significant
abrupt hormonal changes that affect
cardiovascular disease risk so it's
possible that some of these values might
shift even so I'd argue it wouldn't be
enough of a difference to eliminate the
massive benefit even if uh even if that
is just educated speculation on my part
okay one more thing that I think really
Nails the point on how massive these
effects are is a metric called nnt so
number needed to treat this statistic
tells us how many people we need to
treat in this case with sauna and car
good cardiorespiratory Fitness to
prevent one death in this study they
indicate a nnt of four to five so in the
best case every four people treated
prevents one death that is a monstrous
effect the cloaked figure holding the
Scythe is going to be out of work with
those numbers now how do we use this
information well on the
cardiorespiratory front
cardiorespiratory Fitness is most
impacted without a doubt by exercise if
you can increase the quality of your
muscle including your heart and lungs
the diaphragm
you will be in that high
cardiorespiratory fitness category
essentially if you aren't exercising
then you're setting yourself up to be in
that low Camp much faster than someone
who moves their body I'll I'll have more
on that uh shortly as for the sauna it's
pretty simple increasing sauna use to
more than two times per week will do the
trick so the main points here are that
good cardiorespiratory Fitness is the
greatest protective effect against
mortality based on these data but adding
sauna can also provide benefit I also
mentioned I've done a good amount of
study analysis on cardiorespiratory
Fitness and there's actually another
study that indicates that if you can get
your cardiorespiratory Fitness in a
certain range you can extend your life
by a set number of years I cover that
here otherwise there's much more on
sauna as well right here thanks for
tuning in
[Music]